[Music]
something beside
me a light to the
kerosene and the places aren't real
anymore and the faces don't say
anything in the silent
light of the Mind wind blown
sphere it's a
game Devil's chest
[Music]
C Devil's chest
Crow greetings from Devil's chess club
I'm Aaron good today my guest is former
CIA officer and CIA torture whistle
blower John kyaku we're going to be
discussing Russia the Ukraine war the
Moscow terror attack the Gaza genocide
and the Zionist recent deadly attacks on
Iran's Embassy in Syria and on American
Aid workers and we're going to tie all
this into bigger historical issues that
the establishment would prefer us to
forget the cia's covert operations and
the ways the agency Advanced us
imperialism by collaborating with drug
traffickers Jihadi ha networks oil
companies and the intelligence Services
of us client states please check the
show notes for a link to loud and clear
John kaku's substack
Page this episode of Devil's chess club
is available to everyone courtesy of for
died trying the new documentary film
series which explores the extraordinary
lives and cataclysmic assassinations of
JFK Malcolm X Martin Luther King and
Robert F Kennedy there is now a pat page
for for Di trying it offers patrons a
number of other perks including a new
four di trying podcast and access to the
newest film chapter one the world as it
was which is also coming soon to other
major streaming
platforms John Kaku great to have you
back thanks for having me happy to do it
so you are a former CIA officer and your
some of your expertise was in the Middle
East and I think that makes you well
suited to comment on some of these
things that that we've been working on
on the on the American acception podcast
and here on uh we've been discussing it
on Devil's chess club also I want to
first see what you think about some of
the recent events with uh going on with
Israel in this Gaza Gaza I don't want to
call it a war this massive Slaughter
genocide whatever we want to call it and
one of these comes from moon of Alabama
post uh that came out today were're
recording this on April 8th and they say
two Israeli actions misfired pushed
Netanyahu into Retreat and he he's a
wise guy misspelling netanyahu's name
that way but I'll forgive him for that
um he says there's serious signs that
the Israeli government under pressure
from the US is moving towards an
intermediate ceasefire state that all
sides may be able to live with for a
while at least this is split the
Netanyahu government and mayw well in
the Coalition which supports it which I
think is quite plausible considering the
war seems be the only thing keeping him
afloat uh after six months operations in
Gaza uh Israeli government has achieved
none of its objectives Hamas isn't
defeated the hostages haven't been
released there's no plan for who's going
to rule Gaza in the future so it's been
kind of a
disaster what what is your take on the
on this on what what this guy's saying
that these blunders recently the two big
ones he's talking about which I didn't
put in this but it's we're talking about
the killing of those Aid workers and
then the attack on the Iranian Embassy
which is not just a violation of the you
know Geneva or the Vienna conventions VI
convention it's it's worse than that
yeah what do you because I think it's a
pro it's a provocation which is they a
war yes that's that's the only motive
that makes any sense and so what do you
what do you make of of this do you think
that this is really going to be
something that sticks because just the
logic of it it makes no sense for really
Israel or the US to keep persisting in
this way yeah I have a couple of
thoughts uh first of all he's right that
there are real signs that the Israeli
government may not survive this Benny
gance the former Defense Minister who's
now a member of the Israeli War cabinet
was in Washington a week ago two weeks
ago and
um he reportedly told um senior American
officials including uh Secretary of
Defense lyd Austin and Secretary of
State Tony blinkin as well as the um the
National Security adviser that
he was ready to pull out of the war
cabinet and he was ready to withdraw his
party uh the blue and white party from
the emergency Coalition that in and of
itself would be enough to crash the
government now one of the reasons why
Netanyahu does not want that to happen
besides the obvious that he wants at
least some semblance of national unity
in order to continue fighting this thing
um is that if Netanyahu is no longer
prime minister he is again liable for
prosecution on multiple uh felony
corruption indictments and and he's not
the only one who's been indicted his
wife has been indicted for corruption as
well so he has his own selfish reasons
for wanting to keep this war going as
long as possible because it protects him
politically
um to the second
Point uh I think that this uh that this
attack on Gaza and the wholesale
Slaughter of civilians which really is
is what we're seeing was a catastrophic
mistake for Netanyahu for a couple of
reasons number one and and moon of or
Moon of Alabama says it right here
there's no viable plan who if not Hamas
will in future rule the Gaza Strip that
is absolutely correct Joe Biden made a
made a a stupid statement several weeks
ago saying that US policy is that the
Palestinian Authority would um run the
Gaza Strip that is a nonstarter from
before you can get the rest of the
sentence out of your mouth in Gaza they
hate the Palestinian Authority it's
corrupt it's weak it's ineffective and
it's wholly in the pocket of the Israeli
government besides that Mahmud Abbas is
something like 18 years into a four-year
term and so nobody wants him nobody
literally no nobody wants it um if
anything it's
Hamas that would be elected to lead the
West Bank you mean if it was Democratic
if there was a democratic election to be
held in in Palestine so that's just a
nonstarter uh now getting to the point
about the uh the bombing of the Israeli
Consulate in Damascus I think that the
Israelis gave that a lot of forethought
I think that the only only way the
Israelis see themselves winning this
thing is in something like a Samson
scenario where you know going house to
house and mowing down Palestinians and
bulldozing their homes and flattening
Gaza that's that's not really
Gonna Win It win it for them they still
have the West Bank to worry about and
Palestinians are united of course and so
I think that the Israelis think that if
they can draw in the Iranians and hisbah
maybe the syrians
too it would give them reason to perhaps
use nuclear weapons or to raise the
stakes in this conflict to a point that
we've never even considered
before crazy dangerous not just for the
region but for the whole world but I
think that that's what the Israeli
calculus is you know look at what the
Israelis are doing too there's no
turning back from what they've already
done it's not just about ground
troops and
hostages it's about for example you and
I are talking on Monday the 8th of April
uh on Saturday the 6th of April CNN
reported that Israeli doctors told haret
the big Israeli newspaper that they are
now doing an inordinate number of
amputations because Palestinian
prisoners are being cuffed for as long
as six months can you imagine you've
been handcuffed since October and now
you have to have your hands removed
there was another report again from
Israeli doctors to
haret that Palestinian prisoners are
being brought into the hospital they're
being asked which limb they prefer to
keep
and then the other one is crushed in a
vice and then amputated okay that's
that's clearly obviously a crime against
humanity you can't do things like that
it's illegal it's barbaric and they're
doing it anyway and this isn't you know
some Palestinian blogger who's saying
this this is Israeli doctors telling
harits well I think that this is just
the beginning of what the Israelis
intend to do to the Palestinians I think
we haven't seen the the the ultimate in
Israeli uh barbarism against prisoners I
was speaking with a with an Israeli
activist an Israeli human rights
activist a week ago and he said that a
Palestinian uh colleague of his was just
released from prison an Israeli
prison and he said that since October
the 7th Israeli I'm sorry uh Palestinian
prisoners in Israeli prisons have not
not been permitted to walk if you can
imagine they're only permitted to crawl
on their hands and knees and he said
that they've gotten to the point many of
them where they Envy the Gaza
Palestinians because they're dying and
that death is preferable to what's
happening inside Israel's
prisons there's just no excuse for
what's happening yeah I mean I to my
mind the only only thing you can compare
it to with a mechanized modern
industrial nation state carrying out
this kind of you know primitive
Slaughter is Nazi Germany I mean it's a
yeah laban's real and greater Israel
Obsession Master race chosen people it's
so right in your face and the it's the
Israel Lobby their flaks are always
there to like say oh that's the most
offensive thing you could ever say blah
blah blah and at this point fits what
are they going to say after the fact
because think about some of the things
that these ridiculous flaks like the ADL
like remember when they went after uh
ilhan Omar for saying it's all about the
Benjamins and they tried to say like
well that's an anti-semitic Trope
because you're saying that the lobby you
know pays all this money to people which
they obviously do but that's like The
Stereotype that like Jewish people have
all this money and they're controlling
things so naughty naughty but like
obviously lobbying works and it's about
money so it was a ridiculous thing to
begin with but after this genocide the
little things that they accuse people of
it's going to be funny because all of
these people that are Flacks for the
Israel Lobby are all guilty of they're
guilty of crimes against humanity for
advocating for genocide and supporting
this yeah so they're they're essentially
like people who are mass murderers are
guilty of horrible crimes against
humanity just for flacking for this
genocide and they're going to talk about
these little infractions of people who
like maybe made some comment that could
be interpreted as this or that I mean
it's a joke I don't know what they think
they're going to do after this the ADL
is going to be a total laughing stock
after this any serious person will hear
all of their pronouncements and laugh at
these people who are basically genocidal
monsters and they're somehow out there
policing the language and scolding
people for things they do wrong like
you're you're backing a genocide and
terrible crimes against humanity and you
have a job to like go around and tattle
on everyone it's just a joke what do
they think is going to happen in the
after this like and and and you realize
they didn't think it through because
they're insane they're just insane
there's no I don't know any other way to
say it I don't have any sympathy for any
Americans who are like oh I still like
it because I don't know I was
brainwashed for my whole life to like
worship this flag in the state I mean
when you worship a state like a and you
think it's this magical thing that's F
that's a big part of fascism I mean
that's essentially a fascist idea the
like organic State the metaphysical
state so I just I don't see how it's I
think Israel may be done because it's
going to be so Gastly going forward I
mean the younger gener and it's just
going to get worse because you recall
the nurg trials you know you had a while
at the nurg trials where Garing was like
kind of being a bit of a r and tour and
the proceedings seem to be going not as
badly as you would have guessed and then
they showed this film that was made this
documentary well there's going to be a
documentary made about this when the
dust settles and it's going to because
of advances in techn techology there's
going to be so much more material I hope
Abby Martin she should she should be the
one to make it because she did the Gaza
fights for Freedom with great thing to
show anyone who says they should use
nonviolent resistance well we see what
they do you get shot in the leg by
Israeli snipers yeah that's right they
need to document this and we need to
have a full Accounting in some way of
this at least the leadership has to be I
mean at least BB should be in spend the
rest of his life in jail but you know
how do we get to that point how in the
world he's been successful over the
years here in the United States in
convincing people not just people people
and
institutions that any criticism of him
personally is
anti-Semitism is a mystery to me but
maybe this conflict has been so brutal
that it will serve as a wakeup call for
Americans to realize that that there is
no excuse at all under any circumstances
to treat human beings the way the
Netanyahu government is treating
Palestinians you know I went to Israel
it's it's funny I've been to I've been
to literally every Arab country except
Libya everyone in the world um I had
never been to Israel until two years ago
it was the first time i' had gone and
you know you you go to Tel Aviv you're
sitting in the center of Tel Aviv at a
cafe and you look around and you say my
God this place is fantastic it's first
world palm trees beautiful beaches and
then you go to
Palestine and you say my God this is the
world's largest outdoor prison how can
these poor people survive in these
oppressive violent hopeless
conditions and yet they do and I'll tell
you one of the things that we should be
thinking about and maybe even worrying
about is the statement that was made by
by Jared Kushner a couple of weeks ago
about how much he would like to develop
Gaza as a resort beautiful beachfront
property this is extremely dangerous and
it did it didn't just pop off the top of
his head I think this is what the plan
is about it's CRI it's criminal in and
of itself it's it's more evidence of
genocidal intent yeah exactly and about
four weeks ago idar benir the minister
of whatever National Security I guess it
is um uh sponsored legislation in the
Israeli knesset to provide exit visas
for any Palestinian that wants to leave
well the the the policy the Israeli
policy since
1967 is that Palestinians can't leave I
was talking to a Palestinian physician
just a couple of months ago and he said
that uh he was born and raised in Gaza
his parents always stressed education
and so he studied and studied and
studied as hard as he could and he
actually got a scholarship to attend a
French medical school and so he applied
for an exit visa and was denied and he
reapplied every single year for seven
years and then for reasons that he's
never understood they approved him now
the this French school was good enough
to to renew the scholarship every year
for seven years so he went to France got
a medical degree and the Israelis never
let him back in again what he wanted to
do was go back to Gaza and to be a
physician there to treat his people the
Israelis never let him back in so now
it's the opposite that the policy is the
policy is to get everybody out send them
anywhere they want to go just get them
out send them to Jordan or Egypt or the
United States or wherever so that the
Israelis can settle that land right
they'll take it over and turn it over to
to settlers mostly American settlers and
the Jared kushers and Donald Trump so
the world can build resorts in violation
of international law on Palestinian
territory I really believe that that's
the policy it was not an accident that
he just that he just came out with
it right and I don't I mean I it will be
interesting to see if they can pull that
off I don't see how you'd be able to do
that in the with the rest of the world
and with
I think the IC the icj originally handed
down an indictment I mean that was
essentially what the earlier ruling was
and they were they will investigate and
revisit this and it's going to unless
that body is so corrupt that that it's
hopeless yeah then they're going to come
back with a it's so straightforward the
I mean I can't think of another case
like this because there hasn't been any
group that's been as hubristic as the
Israelis about it and when you look back
at it this all it's it's a straight line
from the 90s I mean Netanyahu was the
guy who commissioned the clean break
Report with people like wolfowitz and
Richard uh Richard Pearl Richard Pearl
and this was on the heels of the 92 or
91 insano Paul wolfowitz Pentagon
defense strategy uh yeah paper that was
leaked because HW Bush was not as insane
as these guys uh and they leaked it and
I think that the neocons got their wings
clipped and that's probably why that
could be largely why HW Bush lost in '92
but then a few years later they're
issuing the clean break report you get
the PAC thing it's and they've wanted
this I mean Netanyahu has been obset the
greater Israel idea I guess takes root
largely after the 67 War more more
seriously and that's been everything
they've tried to do they say facts on
the ground it means they've been trying
to do this for a long time and this is
just a final ution and I think that the
problem is yeah it didn't go the way the
neocons had hoped they had their plan of
regime change and you turn Iraq into
maybe a client state or you partition it
which is what Joe Biden wanted to do oh
Aon aarin I'm sorry to interrupt you I
was
sitting I was sitting in a secure video
teleconference at CIA headquarters the
night before we invaded Iraq okay I was
the notetaker in in this this principal
committee meeting so the meeting was
chaired by Dick Cheney um I was there as
the notetaker for for George Tennant who
was the CIA director at the time it
included condalisa rice and Colin Powell
and I forget who the commander of
centcom was and I mean everybody who was
anybody in
Washington including several senior
directors at the National Security
Council were on this this uh video
teleconference and
one one idiot from the NC was one of one
of the CIA director or sorry one of the
senior directors for the Middle East
said and I'll never forget it he said
when we cross that border tomorrow
they're going to throw flowers at us
they're going to throw flowers at us and
when I went back to my office I said to
the deputy director who was my boss I
said have none of these people studied
the Middle East do none of them have any
background in history to think that
we'll be seen as anything but an
occupation Force
that that the Iraqis will throw flowers
at us and another thing when when the
meeting and I've told this this story a
number of times but when the meeting
began um Cheney asked uh sent the the
commander of sencom to uh start the
briefing and to tell you the truth I I
don't like military briefings because I
don't really understand them elements of
the first core are moving here and the
third Army division is moving there and
the platoon is moving this way and that
means nothing to me but then at the end
of The Briefing he says if all goes as
planned we can be in teron by
August and George very discreetly turned
his microphone off and he turned to me
and he said did he say Teran or did he
say
Baghdad and I said uh he said
teron and George says have these people
lost their minds and then he discreetly
turned the microphone back on so at the
the end of the meeting I went back to my
office and the the deputy director said
how'd the meeting go and I said did you
know we were going to attack Iran in in
August and he said H are they still
talking about that he said we're not
going to attack Iran in August these
guys don't know anything about the
Middle East thus the the flowers comment
but here we are a generation later what
I'm talking about this meeting that I'm
talking about happened 22 years ago and
we still haven't learned
anything right I mean they they they and
they are just aren't in the position
they thought they would be in by now I
mean they were supposed to go and put in
a c turn Iraq into a client State Syria
was supposed to go down they failed
there it was dominoes remember it was
gonna be
dominoes and they and and now I I feel
that this is exacerbated by the
recognition because the wolfowitz and
the neocons they're very Pro Zionist
obviously I think that's really the
driving force now I used to think it's
like well it's some sort of Alliance of
and I still think it is an alliance of
crazy right-wing you know militarists
and oil men like and so on yeah that's a
part of it that's a part of it yeah it's
a part of it but the I think the driving
force is has been Zionism and a Hardline
neocon Zionism and they the evangelicals
yes with but but in a socially
engineered kind of way I think that oh
yeah they've put money into Mega
churches and other things like that to
make to Stupify these people because
there's no organic reason that people
would believe something so insane and
stupid even though there's a tradition
of religious fundamentalism in the US
and so on this is so unique and
politically useful that it cannot be a
natural phenomenon it has to have been
created by lots of money I am a little
bit embarrassed to tell you that I
taught as an adjunct um at Liberty
University for four years Liberty
University of course is the world
biggest yeah world's biggest uh
Evangelical University and the reason
they hired me was because of my position
on torture and they said that torture
was not Christian so awesome I taught uh
in the in the Jesse Helms School of
government okay so we disagreed on
99.9% of issues but that one tenth of 1%
that we agreed on was was torture but
one of the things that I
learned is that that American
conservative American evangelicals have
this inexplicably simplistic view of
Israel whereby number one they don't
have the foggiest idea that some
Palestinians are Christians number one
like not the foggiest idea number two
they believe like actually believe in
their hearts that they can hasten the
second coming of Christ that it's within
their power to hasten the second coming
of Christ by forcing all of the world's
Jews back to Israel and so the Israelis
are smart enough to know that they can
exploit this stupidity on the part of
American evangelicals by saying Hey
listen you know if you support Israel we
can give you money for your mega
churches and you can encourage Jews to
come home and now they're joined at the
hip but for wildly different
reasons and it's just it's just like you
have to be halfrain
dead to not see what the Israelis that
the Israelis are playing you but even if
they realized it I don't think they
would
care yeah I mean they they wouldn't
because they would see that it as the
even if they understood they were being
manipulated they would think that the
Israelis were doing it for
they may be doing it for wrong reasons
but they're they're gonna rebuild that
Temple Mount and they're gonna Slaughter
those cow exactly right all the crazy
[__] yeah we were just talking about
slaughtering the cows today exactly
they're going to take the Temple Mount
and they're going to put the Third
Temple up and then we'll see yeah I mean
this is really lunacy and I I'll say
this the voice of reason here is in a
sense Iran uh this this is a picture of
the aftermath of that attack of the on
the Consulate in uh in Syria the Iranian
consulate and the killing of a very
senior irgc commander and this the
analysis here this is from the cradle
but um the political analyst all
political analyst Amal sad says and this
is so obvious this this killing appears
less about employing the madman Theory
to intimidate and deter its adversaries
and more about deliberately embracing a
strategy of chaotic Warfare to escalate
and expand the scope of the conflict so
the US will be forced to directly enter
the war should the hell out of all of us
we were just talking about this and I'll
elaborate on this a little more because
this came in the Jerusalem Post today um
Israel or Iran offers no response to
Damascus strike if us secures Gaza
ceasefire so apparently Iran is behind
the scenes saying we will not respond to
that air strike if you can or you know
negotiate AC fire in Gaza which is to my
mind quite magnanimous and that's some
statesmanship from Iran which we don't
see anything from the US except for you
know lying in a clown show every time
any spokesperson opens their mouth but
here they are what do you think uh what
do you think are the chances that
Hezbollah and Iran working together
could could somehow find a way to
diffuse this without it going into a
wider War because I think that's in
everybody's interest it's in the
Israelis interest if they the Israel's
interest that's right and you know the
both Iran and Hezbollah have to be have
to be lauded for their for their
restraint R from the very beginning of
this it's incredible to me that we
haven't
seen almost the immediate expansion of
the conflict and we haven't and it's
because the Iranians and Hezbollah have
been so um so unwilling to take the
Israeli bait and to respond to Israel's
provocation or provocative uh actions um
now the Iranians told us through the
Swiss uh uh intersection the US
intersection at the Swiss Embassy in tan
they told us late last week that they
intended to respond to the Israeli
attack but they saw this as a
state-to-state attack that required a
state-to-state response they would not
use Shia militias in Iraq or Syria or
Yemen to strike back at Israel this
would be a state response number one
number two they said that they had no
intention of hitting a US Target that
this was between Iran and Israel and
they wanted to tell us in advance now
can you remember a previous time when
the Iranian government would proactively
offer up assurances like this to the
American government because I can't so I
think that the
Iranians I think that the Iranians
should be applauded for the way they've
handled this thing now the Israelis
deserve to be smacked for what they did
in in Damascus and whatever the Iranians
end up doing in retaliation the Israelis
have earned
it I mean the the chances of Israel
getting what it deserves are so small
anyway but whatever does will be a part
of that yeah yeah yeah but uh you know I
think that I think you're exactly
correct that the ultimate Israeli goal
is to drag the United States into this
no matter how bad it gets I don't think
they really care how far down the road
it goes including with the employment of
nuclear weapons I think that the goal
the ultimate goal is is to bring the US
in yeah and China China and Russia have
made statements to the effect that they
will if it comes down to it protect the
sovereignty and the existence of the
Iranian state so yes this would be
bringing in this would be essentially
nuclear doomsday if that comes down to
that yes and this is again so not so
difficult to game out and yet there
doesn't seem to be that ability anymore
and that's what is frightening about
this it's bad enough when you had all
these cold war game War or Game Theory
machine mind people who were kind of
lunatics but at least you felt like they
could at least predict sometimes that if
you did X and Y then Z might happen you
know yes some accuracy they don't gain
they've lost that ability and that's
what is frightening to me because the
part of the reason I was skeptical that
the Ukraine war would ever break out is
because I didn't see it at all as being
in the US interest for something like
that to happen it didn't make any sense
to me at all if I'd been reading
Consortium news more which I normally
did at the time I would have said oh
yeah it is this a good chance this is
gonna happen I didn't say like oh it'll
never happen but I thought like I don't
think that they will invade because I
think that it doesn't make any sense for
the US to provoke an invasion because
how could you possibly beat uh Russia
with Ukraine you intervene more then you
have a nuclear war and that's what I
thought at the time and I was that's
obviously the case like that's been the
case and so what the what what are we
doing there and why is Israel doing this
when it's similarly like if they murder
everyone uh in Gaza they will destroy
themselves because the whole world will
be a gas if they start a war with Iran
it could lead a nuclear war that's a
disaster there's no good solution to
this so why the hell are they doing the
things that they're doing yeah you're
exactly right I don't want to get too
far off uh off of uh Israel and
Palestine but you rais a good point
about about Ukraine and you know it
makes you wonder what in the world
Emanuel macron's uh thinking when he
says he wants to send French combat
troops to uh to Ukraine that would be an
act of war and it would it would draw
NATO including the United States uh
directly into that war just like the
Israelis want to draw the United States
into their War none of it makes any
sense none of it and you're right what
in the world would make the United
States think that Ukraine could beat
Russia a nuclear power and one of the
three most powerful countries in the
world and to what end why do we need
Ukraine to be in NATO we
don't we don't besides the fact that we
repeatedly promised the Russians over
the course of what three or four
different presidential Administration
ations that we would not expand NATO to
Russia's border and we did it multiple
times multiple times and they finally
had to put their foot down yeah this is
this gets into what I the parallels I
see there and it's been a bit shocking
to me I'm going to talk to you a little
bit about some of the things that we've
done because it involves CIA uh that
we've been working on at the podcast and
we have a series coming up with uh my
friend Ben Howard who has co-authored
things with me and Peter Scott uh in the
past and uh we're looking at Peter Dale
Scott's 2005 article on the Global Drug
meta group and it deals with this
military contractor outfit called Far
West which was something of a successor
to BCCI and it involved all of these
characters um that that were that
included people who planned the Russian
911 of 2000 which started off the second
chin war and it it really gets into this
whole postc Cold War era that I I think
people do not well understand and that
I'm only trying to sort of look at some
of this work and obscure work and make
sense of what happened but I now think
that what and I think your story
actually fits into this and I'll try to
explain how uh I think that the big
conflict in the in George HW Bush's
administration because I used to hear um
Lawrence Wilkerson and Rey McGovern say
that HW Bush always called the neocons
The Crazies right and said oh they're
they're dreaming up crazy [__] in the B
and then you had the the wolfa witz
insano version of the defense plan which
was basically like the PAC Manifesto
except it was like eight years before
Pac where he was just saying that the
wolfowitz doctrine we got to make sure
that no power could possibly challenge
American uh Global dominance and then
this was too crazy for bush bush is a
guy and and a family that people on the
left who are study these you know
Imperial chicanery and covert operations
and all this we think bush is pretty
Sinister but I I think actually and I
and I don't dispute that he is and that
he's part of that American waspy
establishment that did a lot of terrible
things but this neocon group is
different and they are worse and they
were they were chastened when not only
did Bush leaked that to the press and
put the kibos on Wolowitz's crazy plan
for world domination but they also Bush
also HW Bush also told the Israelis that
they need to negotiate a two-state
solution seriously or they're not going
to get these loan guarantees and no
president had done that it got written
up in Israel that like this maybe is
maybe why he lost and bush shouldn't
have uh you know betrayed his Israel
Israeli friends so I think that there
was a conflict that involved the upper
echelons of the US at this time and that
some of these investigations that came
out like BCCI or the Danny coolero
whoever it was that was feeding him
information and it tied into some of
these people I think that there was a
struggle between that old waspy mobbed
up American establishment that George
Bush and Allan dullas and other people
represent and then the neocons which are
American Hardline right-wingers
militarists you know people like Cheney
or historically people like scoop
Jackson and so on uh and then but merged
with the Israel Lobby and that this was
really the big conflict and I think some
of it involved covert operations in a
sense and who would control them I think
that the US back at different times was
more involved with the kind of Mafia
type operations and that when these
scandals happen just as they did in the
70s they kind of get offshored in
different ways and I think that you look
at Epstein and you think what does
Epstein represent he's intelligence but
he's also got all these Israel
connections I think Israel's been
running a lot of these crazy operations
or the neocons have and I it would be
really interesting to know to what
extent these are handled by CIA the CIA
and the American side or was there some
sort of high level decision to Outsource
these to a kind
of intelligence mob Mafia sort of thing
I mean it it actually makes me wonder go
back and look at what were the Zionist
and Israeli connections to like the
Lansky Syndicate and so on over years
and I don't think that we've ever we've
never really fully investigated the
relationship between the mob and the
intelligence agencies and what the hell
they were doing
in the 90s who was approving it who was
running it was it the US and the
Pentagon and CIA or was it a neocon sort
of
international with you know perhaps with
guidance from mad and so on it's you
look at these events and they are hard
to explain except with reference to a
conflict sort of like Watergate and like
I think that HW Bush was removed by
similar forces that removed Nixon
because Nixon seems to have been I mean
who was it that's there the aftermath of
Nixon's resignation under the Ford
Administration it's Cheney and Rumsfeld
and they fire all the regular
right-wingers and they bring in neocon
type people so this is like a a part of
our history that is important and nobody
really has written the definitive or
even a definitive strong version of it
that's your next book you know I'll tell
you um Arabs say all the time uh well
Arab diplomats Arab intellectuals
political figures will tell you all the
time that there have only been two
presidents in American history that gave
the Arabs a fair shake and that was
Dwight Eisenhower and George HW Bush and
that was it that was it in all of
American History they say that those are
the two the two presidents that they
could trust not that they could trust
the people that surrounded those
Presidents J they should add JFK to that
though he NASA NASA wept and uh and was
despondent for days when Kennedy was
killed and Kennedy was trying to stop
them from getting nuclear weapons and he
was trying to solve the Palestinian
question and a total 180 after the fact
that's true that's true yeah that's true
uh but you're right the you know the the
wolfowitz Cheney Rumsfeld uh my God all
Pearl you know there's there's a famous
story that that on September 11th um
Richard Pearl was at the White House and
he said uh you know we have to attack
Iraq and uh several several of the NSC
people said we don't think Iraq did this
and he said I don't care who did it we
have to attack
Iraq and that was the
policy I mean Sam Huntington wrote in I
think it's in Clash of the civilizations
he says Iraq is the only country that
could challenge like Western hemony in
the Middle East uh because Iraq has
agricultural capacity with those famous
river banks and delas and uh they have
some industry and some social services
and so on and so I think that's what
really those sanctions were about in the
90s where they were just let's keep
Iraqi oil off the market let's not let
that country develop let's just make it
a basket case because it's we're better
off that way and that was the policy
that was the policy during the Iran Iraq
war too where you support both sides you
give intelligence especially overhead
imagery to both sides you provide
weapons to both sides because you want
that war to go on forever so they
completely destroy each other and then
you don't have to do it give another
example Casey used to make a joke he
used to say oh yeah we're fing both
sides so they'll kill each other yeah um
in in 2008 and again in 2011 I went to
Afghanistan to study the heroin poy crop
I was the chief investigator on the
Senate Foreign Relations Committee at
the time and so um I went with h with a
guy from DEA and with a couple of
military guys and we went to kahar and
to Helman prop SL Gara where they grow
most of the heroin Poppy and the bottom
line was this Afghanistan produces
93% of the world's
heroin almost all of that heroin goes to
Iran and Russia and so when I said wow
you know why don't we do something to
stop you know encourage them to to grow
things with two growing Seasons I said
grow onions and tomatoes and
pomegranates um we we could provide the
SE seeds we could provide the the
fertilizer we don't want them to grow
vegetables we want Iranians and Russians
to be hooked on Heroin and the truth is
that Iran has the highest rate of opioid
Addiction in the world and Russia has
the second highest rate in the world
just the way we want
it yeah I mean it's it's really wild
what the US has done with drugs I mean
when they there was a little bit of a
push back with Nixon's War on Drugs and
he shut down the the air America you
know drug
connection basically it got exposed by
Peter Peter Del Scott really Alfred
McCoy's famous for but it was really
Peter it was Al Al McCoy's story is that
um it was the poet Allan Ginsburg that
that turned him on to this but Alan
Ginsburg actually wrote to Peter a
letter and said hey I heard you've been
talking about this could you send me
material on the uh on the dope trade in
the CIA and he and Peter did and then
then he Peter and then Ginsburg talks to
McCoy I think McCoy may have been
writing something of a limited hangout
in a sense but that's a whole other
story they suppressed Peter's book which
was the better one and the more incisive
one I think the war conspiracy it gets
uh they they hold it off for two years
they don't publish it and it turns out
that the Publishing House in the middle
of Indiana which published some anti-war
people for strange reasons and the one
that held Peter's book so that Al
McCoy's book would come out first that
place that publishing house was called
Bob's Marill and the legal council for
it was William Harvey of the CIA one of
the most notorious you know murderous
individuals ever so it's really wild but
Peter has wrote in 2003 before he wrote
this book about Far West and the Global
Drug meta group he wrote drugs oil in
war and he noticed that you know
pipelines and weapons and uh drugs they
they keep they overlap in US foreign
policy over and over again this pi here
in the graphic is Camp Bond steel which
was built in 19 you know after the Koso
war and I want to give you a little bit
of a timeline here and see what you you
think of this in the context of the
neocon uh you know takeover of US
foreign policy so a lot of this has to
there were pipeline routes and so on
this is Peter's you know drugs oil and
War thesis you had in 1991 this gets
into what I'd call the neocon
international and it's it's relevant to
Ukraine it's to all this in 1991 there
was a coup there was a a
strange entity set up in aeran called
Mega oil it was oil companies and people
like Richard Secord and Ed Dearborn from
Iran Contra you know xcia guys yep and
they set up an airline uh just like it
like the air America more or less and
they started flying in jihadis and uh
cin groups and Albanian groups became
involved in the heroin traffic they were
facilitating these things and eventually
they stay jaku in aeran and they pull it
out of the Russian orbit and into the US
orbit there's a aeran chamber of
commerce with people like Dick Cheney
and Richard Armitage on it and it just
becomes like a you know a sort of
principality of the neocon international
basically and they want these pipelines
uh that there's these pipelines planned
to get azerbajan gas to the Black Sea or
through turkey and you can see this ad
BP just launched a big aeran gas pipel
line they they call it the Shad Den to
gas Fields after the British puppet you
know that the CIA
reinstalled so it's really it's it's
ridiculous but we see that part and you
know it leads to the chin War which you
see that like Putin has said a couple
times now hey you guys were backing
these jihadis why were you doing that
when you're supposed to be fighting this
war on terror a good question and then
additionally on the the further side on
the other side of the Black Sea you have
a a plan for this ambo pipeline which
never really comes through but there's
still other versions of it that they're
trying to get get through but it was
ambo because it's Albania Macedonia and
Bulgaria oil pipeline right that's the
ambo and this was a this was at the same
time and then a part of uh the coast of
the operations in Yugoslavia you have
Camp Bond steel set up and that becomes
a big hub for heroin right so you have
these us operations with jihadis in
aeran in Chia and they're all doing
things to facilitate what the US wants
in Kosovo the K is there a terrorist
organization Mafia and their partner on
the ground is al- Qaeda led by Muhammad
alahi no less in 1998 1999 and I put a
little X here on the graphic to show
where Camp Bond steel is but it's
basically not just guarding these uh
sort of presides over these oil pipeline
routes that are very strategic uh but
also heroin went in and out of there and
all sorts of other illicit traffics with
uh the the ALB the Kos ofar Mafia
basically and it was like they this was
this whole neocon foreign policy and
these entities like Far West Military
contractors working with chin uh
Warlords and drug dealers and people
that were in Russian you know Russian
officials but people that were not Putin
Putin loyalists people that were more
loyal to yelton and Bowski basically
Western
Stooges and uh this all seems to be part
of this neocon International and when
you now we're seeing like these same
sort of entities like Tajikistan people
attacking uh Moscow and then trying to
flee to Ukraine yeah uh it's like they
they it really is this kind of this sort
of fascist force in the US it's like a
it's I I just call it the parap fascist
Neo International because it's like it's
a way that you can have the essentially
like a global fur principle where you
just break whatever laws you want all
the time except you just say we didn't
do that like we have all these policies
we're just like oh no we don't we didn't
do that but they they are using these
jihadis and then you turn around to 911
and then all of a sudden it becomes the
reason for like actually going over
there and putting more military bases in
all these same places because the same
groups they've been you know supporting
supposedly are attacking us but then our
only remedy is to go and do all these
things we wanted to do in the energy
heartlands of the world anyway I mean
it's it's a
scandal with it's needs to be
investigated and yet we're we can't do
anything about it we're just like uh we
see what they want with the NATO
expansion we see what the neocons want
with these what the zionists want who
are the main really force behind the
Neons we see how insane they are with
Gaza and I feel like the 21st century
and even the the post Cold War era was a
was sort of a a kind of mobbed up uh
foreign policy adventure to try to take
over the whole world and it just failed
and now we're seeing that it fall apart
it's run a ground on Israel I mean Iraq
and Afghanistan first but Israel Syria
uh you know Gaza I mean Ukraine it's all
fall falling apart and I don't see how
they can salvage it so what what what do
we do with these this history that's a
fake history and fake news day today
and it doesn't matter because no matter
how much they lie about it we're still
at this point where everything's falling
apart
anyway yeah what can we do I
mean in a perfect world we could rely on
the Congressional oversight committees
to ensure that this kind of thing
doesn't happen but that that doesn't
work it's never it's never worked at
least besides um working very briefly in
1975 and
76 uh it's just not worked uh so how
much that worked I question how much
that worked at all because I now think
more that some of the function of that
was to take covert operations and move
make them even further removed I
actually think that some of the people
that were behind the the the Freedom of
Information Act may have been working
along similar lines like if you make it
so the US is not able to carry out Co
operations because there's a little bit
of a fear of Congress or whatever then
the the response of the people running
the US is not like well we're going to
have to be lawful it's that they're
going to have to Outsource some of these
things yeah I think drive it deep
underground and I and I think that
Israel has been a major repository and
Driver of of the of this that they've
that they've taken over a lot of the
things that the CIA might have wanted to
do in the past I think that some of
these investigations had a weird side to
them of like really trying to to to make
it so the US can't carry out cover
operations so has to rely on these other
these other outfits and that gives them
power otherwise it's hard to it's hard
to totally understand how Israel can
bend the US to its will I don't think
they totally control it because I think
the us is going to push back because
this is so disastrous but man it it's
it's definitely not like a a normal
relationship between countries and I
think that the clandestine part of it is
is is important and yet it's never
really been told because of course it's
all secret yes yeah and it'll always be
secret you know it's one of the what
what it is called the holy of holies in
the uh in the intelligence committee you
can't ever talk about sources and
methods you can't ever talk about
liaison relationships and you can't talk
about anything having to do with NSA but
sources and
methods is it completely encompasses uh
covert action they don't even like
saying the words covert action right you
can't even really speak the words covert
action when you're when you're inside
the CIA that's how secretive it is so
yeah I think you're right I think that
we've we've put ourselves in a position
where we probably are Outsourcing a lot
of these cover action programs there is
no oversight and even if there was
oversight I think that that the um
oversight committee members in both the
house and the Senate have either been so
co-opted that they just buy in or
they've been so
cowed that they don't
object so what do the people that you
are in cont I don't know how many people
with the agency are still in contact
with but I there's supposed to be
dispassionate realists supposed to be
are there do you hear any realists who
are like able to look at the United
States position and how it has
deteriorated so much and how our
possibilities are are going to have to
be narrowed a good bit and our Ambitions
scaled back are is is that even setting
into or is there such a group think and
a kind of enforced Conformity that
nobody really says like this whole thing
has been a quest for Empire and it's
failed we got to deal with it is anybody
saying that no uh they're not group
think is a big problem but you'll get
former CIA officers to say that until
the cows come home but people who are
still active in the CIA no they they
would never be so
self-reflective absolutely not that's
why that's why people like like Ray
McGovern for example or Fulton Armstrong
are such gems because they they speak
freely then they were senior officers
they were senior intelligence service
officers um so they they know of what
they speak but among people who were
still actively CIA absolutely
not right it's just this this alarming
sense that there's
nobody who is sensible looking at these
these things I just it's and acade
academics are bad even leftist anti
imperialists are often very blinkered
strangely some one of the best people
out there is Jeff Sachs I mean he he
actually sounds like he is summarizing
my own like dissertation in his broad
arguments it's actually remarkable I
mean I wrote in 2015 that the US is
basically Lawless top- down uh state
that is bent on world domination and has
institutionalized the uh abnation of the
rule of law and uh through cover op
operations and everything else and so on
he now says similar things and he says
similar things about JFK he even talks
about the you know the Jihadi operations
in the 90s and such and uh it's it's so
jarring to listen to them compared to
all the other academics it's just
they've really created a totalitarian
system where whether you're in Academia
or anywhere else you every incentive if
you want to advance is to uh accept
really the big lie over and over again
different big lies uh in general and
it's I don't know how we overcome this
except without with some sort of defeat
but when we're a nuclear armed Nation
that's a dicey proposition yeah you can
say that again look at the risk of
miscalculation it's almost not worth
taking and and I don't you just it's you
there seem to be no adults in the in the
room the the Biden Biden and Trump both
are are insane uh and they don't hire
anyone who is able to say anything the
best guy is John Kirby only because he
looks so uncomfortable he looks like a
sitcom character with that smirk on his
face all the time like it's slapstick
but like there's nobody that's sensible
in speaking truth about these things at
all yeah sad but
true so I I but I think that things that
can't go on forever don't and so that is
something to make note of but what does
that mean it just is like that saying
like things can't if things are going to
stay the same they're going to have to
change a lot you know like that joke
right so but and I can accept that but
what does that
mean it's almost like Yogi Bara is is
telling us what we need to what we need
to focus on that's what we need as
president he's dead but maybe with AI we
can somehow resurrect him and that we
make him our president well John uh I
want to thank you very much for um for
taking the time to talk to us today uh
where can people follow your work I know
you're on Sputnik anything else you want
to talk about here oh yeah thanks I I'm
on sput Nick I've got a weekly Tv show
uh that's uh syndicated in 33 countries
but the easiest way to uh to find any of
it is on substack at John kiraku thanks
for having excellent I will put links in
the show notes and uh as ever I
appreciate you uh spending time with us
thanks so much Aon it's a
pleasure thanks to Dana chavaria for
producing this episode and thank you for
tuning in you can buy or rent the for D
trying prologue now on Amazon and other
streaming platforms chapter one is also
available now visit for.com for details
please do subscribe to the American
exception podcast on patreon for first
access to all Devil's chess club
episodes and for all new and past
episodes of the American exception
podcast including new episodes of our
Peter Dell Scott oral history series and
this series on Far West which we
discussed during the show one thing I
meant to mention before getting a little
sidetracked uh it's about and his CIA
torture whistleblowing ordeal I
mentioned this in the past but I wanted
to mention it again it's related to my
thesis that the end of the Cold War
began a new deep State conflict in the
US the waspy US establishment of people
like the Rockefellers Dean aers Allan
Dulles binski George HW Bush basically
the US establishments Imperial
realists versus what we can call the
neoconservatives or the neocon parap
fascist
International I believe that what
happened during this time period around
0506 was that pressure from the neocons
was building to go into Iran to go
further than they had before they wanted
to start a whole bunch of different Wars
they eventually would get their way with
Wars in uh Syria and Libya but for at
the time they really wanted to go into
Iran which John was talking about
earlier I think that was the cont text
in which John Superior uh set things in
motion for John to be put in this place
where he ends up blowing the whistle on
torture despite not really setting out
to do that at the
outset he ended up going to jail for
this and was the only person prosecuted
uh for the torture regime created by
Dick Cheney and George W bush which is
really something that's a perfect
American thing the only people that get
punished for uh Major Crimes are those
who expose them because it's essentially
a criminal
regime so I think in some John Superior
may have essentially sacrific Jon as
part of an establishment campaign to
undercut the neocon W Bush
Administration before they could go into
Iran or before they could stage a terror
spectacle to blame on Iran John kyaku
for the bigger cause may have had to go
to prison but the war with Iran was
avoided Rumsfeld was soon replaced as
Secretary of Defense and the neocons had
their wings clipped for a moment in
other words Jon was treated like a Pawn
on the devil's chessboard